<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/coderdojo/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2024-10-21T20:02:08+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/coderdojo/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">CoderLevelUp | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Levelling up our coding community, in Africa.</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Volunteers needed at coding clubs</title>
      <link href="/volunteers-needed" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Volunteers needed at coding clubs" />
      <published>2023-05-09T00:30:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-05-09T00:30:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/volunteers-needed</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/volunteers-needed">&lt;p&gt;Helping young people develop new skills and explore their creativity is very
rewarding. Also, it’s a lot of fun!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Code Club &amp;amp; CoderDojo are free volunteer-led coding clubs for young people that are always looking for volunteers!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;we-need-your-help&quot;&gt;We need your help!&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You could become a mentor and help young people learn to code. To help beginners, you don’t even need technical skills!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You could also help with setting up the space and recording attendance for the club sessions. You could help a club run its social media presence or website!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;venues-in-western-cape&quot;&gt;Venues in Western Cape&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Code Club has been growing in schools thanks to the efforts of Anelisa together with WCED and SADTU and we now (May 2024) 
have 90+ school clubs and 4 community Coderdojos in the Western Cape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re curious to see if there is already a club near you, you can check out:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;code club: &lt;a href=&quot;https://codeclub.org/en/clubs?clubs_search%5Bcountry%5D=ZA&amp;amp;clubs_search%5Bq%5D=cape+town&amp;amp;commit=Find+a+Code+Club&quot;&gt;find a Code Club&lt;/a&gt; (change the location and range to find more clubs)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CoderDojo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://coderdojo.com/en/find?search=cape+town&amp;amp;distance=50&amp;amp;unit=miles&amp;amp;lat=&amp;amp;lng=&quot;&gt;find a Dojo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even more venues coming soon:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Schools: Our Region has has 1500 schools, 97% with computer rooms with internet, and we’ve partnering with WCED to train teachers to start clubs, so more schools coming soon.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Libraries: we’re piloting &lt;a href=&quot;https://help.coderdojo.com/cdkb/s/article/CoderDojo-in-the-library&quot;&gt;CoderDojo in the Library&lt;/a&gt; with Cape Town City Libraries identifying an initial 5-10 libraries, which means any of the 104 (yep!) libraries in the city will be potential pilots, and ultimately we’d like to see them all running.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;volunteering&quot;&gt;Volunteering&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we’re growing, and venues are opening up to be willing to host or starting clubs more volunteers are needed. More volunteers at clubs help get a better outcome for young people across the network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re here to help you be a great volunteer, whether you’re a coder, an educator, a parent or anything in-between.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More info on volunteering:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://codeclub.org/en/volunteer&quot;&gt;https://codeclub.org/en/volunteer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://coderdojo.com/en/volunteer&quot;&gt;https://coderdojo.com/en/volunteer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Training for 1st time volunteers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ideally please do this 30 min safeguarding e-learning module. &lt;a href=&quot;https://projects.raspberrypi.org/en/projects/safeguarding-module/&quot;&gt;https://projects.raspberrypi.org/en/projects/safeguarding-module/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Training for mentoring (helping young people with code):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a good one to review on how / where you’ll be helping. &lt;a href=&quot;https://projects.raspberrypi.org/en/projects/dojo-mentoring/&quot;&gt;https://projects.raspberrypi.org/en/projects/dojo-mentoring/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Specifically, we’ll start most newcomers on “space talk”, the first step in the scratch pathway, that you can play through here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://projects.raspberrypi.org/en/projects/space-talk&quot;&gt;https://projects.raspberrypi.org/en/projects/space-talk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plus there’ll be lots of friendly fellow mentors and teachers along on the journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to volunteer, (or start a club at your school, or donate, or anything else you can imagine to help), please fill in this &lt;a href=&quot;https://forms.gle/q9p7D1rM3CT7Upsj8&quot;&gt;Coder:Levelup Volunteer details&lt;/a&gt; form or mail &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:volunteer@coderlevelup.org&quot;&gt;volunteer@coderlevelup.org&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Campey</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="codeclub" />
      
        <category term="coderdojo" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Helping young people develop new skills and explore their creativity is very rewarding. Also, it’s a lot of fun! Code Club &amp;amp; CoderDojo are free volunteer-led coding clubs for young people that are always looking for volunteers! We need your help! You could become a mentor and help young people learn to code. To help beginners, you don’t even need technical skills! You could also help with setting up the space and recording attendance for the club sessions. You could help a club run its social media presence or website! Venues in Western Cape Code Club has been growing in schools thanks to the efforts of Anelisa together with WCED and SADTU and we now (May 2024) have 90+ school clubs and 4 community Coderdojos in the Western Cape. If you’re curious to see if there is already a club near you, you can check out: code club: find a Code Club (change the location and range to find more clubs) CoderDojo: find a Dojo Even more venues coming soon: Schools: Our Region has has 1500 schools, 97% with computer rooms with internet, and we’ve partnering with WCED to train teachers to start clubs, so more schools coming soon. Libraries: we’re piloting CoderDojo in the Library with Cape Town City Libraries identifying an initial 5-10 libraries, which means any of the 104 (yep!) libraries in the city will be potential pilots, and ultimately we’d like to see them all running. Volunteering As we’re growing, and venues are opening up to be willing to host or starting clubs more volunteers are needed. More volunteers at clubs help get a better outcome for young people across the network. We’re here to help you be a great volunteer, whether you’re a coder, an educator, a parent or anything in-between. More info on volunteering: https://codeclub.org/en/volunteer https://coderdojo.com/en/volunteer Training for 1st time volunteers: Ideally please do this 30 min safeguarding e-learning module. https://projects.raspberrypi.org/en/projects/safeguarding-module/ Training for mentoring (helping young people with code): a good one to review on how / where you’ll be helping. https://projects.raspberrypi.org/en/projects/dojo-mentoring/ Specifically, we’ll start most newcomers on “space talk”, the first step in the scratch pathway, that you can play through here: https://projects.raspberrypi.org/en/projects/space-talk Plus there’ll be lots of friendly fellow mentors and teachers along on the journey.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A coder’s journey</title>
      <link href="/coderjourney" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A coder's journey" />
      <published>2020-03-15T10:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-03-15T10:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/coderjourney</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/coderjourney">&lt;h1 id=&quot;a-coders-journey&quot;&gt;A coder’s journey&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kylie is 6, missing 2 front teeth, and is loving code club. Her current focus is Sploder; an arcade game that gives agency to the child by allowing the player to choose whatever monsters or challenges they want their character to face. The player builds the shape of the landscape, the “energy” rewards, the challenges to overcome and then plays their game. We have evolved a lot since the 80s arcade!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sploder was not Kylie’s entry point for learning to code. There are some amazing games and apps out there, and her first toe-dip was an incredible game called Sprite Box. We live in a world of abstractions, you want to travel from A to B, and there is a bus company, train service, taxi, or car manufacturer who is handing out the solution to get you there. You, quite literally, do not have to worry about the mechanics of how to travel. Learning to code has undergone a similar revolution in abstraction. Kids do not need to write to learn to create algorithms or loops. With Sprite Box, kids do not even have to be able to read to grasp coding concepts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sprite box challenges the young coder to create solutions using pre-set methods while forcing them to practice DRY (do not repeat yourself) techniques by limiting the number of actions that they may apply. From the start, Kylie was forced to consider what behaviours her little robot, responsible for assisting her (male or female) character to complete her mission of repairing her space ship, was going to do. The concept of enforcing efficiency in code by building functions to call was implicit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kylie joined in on this adventure at Coder Dojo, a weekly club held at the Cape Town Science Centre for kids interested in coding. As an ex-high school teacher, I find Coder Dojo a relaxing place to hang out because it fits all of my educational desires for any child. This is a pull education, not a push education. There is no curriculum, and the children simply follow their interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are kids immersed in Minecraft, Raspberry pie builds, or apps such as Scratch, Algorithm City, Sploder, and Ozaria. They may be found designing their own website or troubleshooting their python code. What they are involved in depends entirely on what their interests are. They work in groups, and they work alone. What is clearly apparent to an ex-mainstream teacher, is that they are all avidly involved in their work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is your child interested in coding? Do you perhaps have no idea whether your child is interested in coding? Either way, feel welcome and come and join in.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>m4sterbunny</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="coderdojo" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">A coder’s journey Kylie is 6, missing 2 front teeth, and is loving code club. Her current focus is Sploder; an arcade game that gives agency to the child by allowing the player to choose whatever monsters or challenges they want their character to face. The player builds the shape of the landscape, the “energy” rewards, the challenges to overcome and then plays their game. We have evolved a lot since the 80s arcade! Sploder was not Kylie’s entry point for learning to code. There are some amazing games and apps out there, and her first toe-dip was an incredible game called Sprite Box. We live in a world of abstractions, you want to travel from A to B, and there is a bus company, train service, taxi, or car manufacturer who is handing out the solution to get you there. You, quite literally, do not have to worry about the mechanics of how to travel. Learning to code has undergone a similar revolution in abstraction. Kids do not need to write to learn to create algorithms or loops. With Sprite Box, kids do not even have to be able to read to grasp coding concepts. Sprite box challenges the young coder to create solutions using pre-set methods while forcing them to practice DRY (do not repeat yourself) techniques by limiting the number of actions that they may apply. From the start, Kylie was forced to consider what behaviours her little robot, responsible for assisting her (male or female) character to complete her mission of repairing her space ship, was going to do. The concept of enforcing efficiency in code by building functions to call was implicit. Kylie joined in on this adventure at Coder Dojo, a weekly club held at the Cape Town Science Centre for kids interested in coding. As an ex-high school teacher, I find Coder Dojo a relaxing place to hang out because it fits all of my educational desires for any child. This is a pull education, not a push education. There is no curriculum, and the children simply follow their interests. There are kids immersed in Minecraft, Raspberry pie builds, or apps such as Scratch, Algorithm City, Sploder, and Ozaria. They may be found designing their own website or troubleshooting their python code. What they are involved in depends entirely on what their interests are. They work in groups, and they work alone. What is clearly apparent to an ex-mainstream teacher, is that they are all avidly involved in their work. Is your child interested in coding? Do you perhaps have no idea whether your child is interested in coding? Either way, feel welcome and come and join in.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">About CoderDojo</title>
      <link href="/coderdojo" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="About CoderDojo" />
      <published>2019-10-14T10:30:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-10-14T10:30:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/coderdojo</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/coderdojo">&lt;p&gt;Free coding clubs for young people, practicing coding from first steps through projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coder:LevelUp is the regional growth partner for the CoderDojo Foundation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://coderdojo.com/&quot;&gt;coderdojo.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://zen.coderdojo.com/find?q=cape%20town&amp;amp;p=1&quot;&gt;Map &amp;amp; links to CoderDojos in Cape Town&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Audience&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7-17 year olds&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Local history&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Started in SA in 2012, weekly classes ever since, 20 dojos in SA today&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Support from&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;afrolabs, ORT Robotics, CoderDojo Foundation, Rotary,&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Key people&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;David Campey, Whitney Tennant, + more mentors&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Campey</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="coderdojo" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Free coding clubs for young people, practicing coding from first steps through projects. Coder:LevelUp is the regional growth partner for the CoderDojo Foundation.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
