<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title> - Articles</title>
    <description>Levelling up our coding community, in Africa.</description>
    <link>
    </link>
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Coolest Projects South Africa 2024</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;Coolest Projects is the world’s leading technology fair for young people. This year for the fifth time in Africa!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;when&quot;&gt;When?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;1100am-9-nov-2024&quot;&gt;11:00am 9 Nov 2024&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;where&quot;&gt;Where?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year we’re delighted to announce that our Cape Town event will have 2 satellite events in Kwa-Zulu Natal and the Eastern Cape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;wc-cape-town-tbc&quot;&gt;WC: Cape Town: [TBC]&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;kzn-durban-blue-roof-the-bluff&quot;&gt;KZN: Durban: Blue Roof, the Bluff.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ec-east-london-mmeli&quot;&gt;EC: East London: MMELI&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;how-do-i-enter&quot;&gt;How do I enter?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Register here: 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://forms.gle/N4jmz7swTnH4TVN46&quot;&gt;Coolest Projects 2024 South Africa Entry Form&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2024 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /coolestprojects2024</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/coolestprojects2024</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Code Club Resources</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;Resources to support your club.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Content, printables and more! From Raspberry Pi, Google, Microsoft, MIT, and DBE.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jul 2024 14:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /codeclub-resources</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/codeclub-resources</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Coolest Projects South Africa 2023</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;Coolest Projects is the world’s leading technology fair for young people. This year for the fourth time in Africa!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;when&quot;&gt;When?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;1111am-11-nov-2023&quot;&gt;11:11am 11 Nov 2023&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why the weird time? Glad you asked! It let’s us write the time as:
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;11:11 11/11&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;where&quot;&gt;Where?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;cape-town-science-centre&quot;&gt;Cape Town Science Centre&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Delighted to announce CTSC as our venue for this year, we can show our projects along with all the cool science stuff!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;how-do-i-enter&quot;&gt;How do I enter?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Register here: 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://forms.gle/EQquPXA5VeXujSpC7&quot;&gt;Coolest Projects 2023 South Africa Entry Form&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Mon, 11 Sep 2023 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /coolestprojects2023</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/coolestprojects2023</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Volunteers needed at coding clubs</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;Helping young people develop new skills and explore their creativity is very
rewarding. Also, it’s a lot of fun!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Code Club &amp;amp; CoderDojo are free volunteer-led coding clubs for young people that are always looking for volunteers!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;we-need-your-help&quot;&gt;We need your help!&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You could become a mentor and help young people learn to code. To help beginners, you don’t even need technical skills!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You could also help with setting up the space and recording attendance for the club sessions. You could help a club run its social media presence or website!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;venues-in-western-cape&quot;&gt;Venues in Western Cape&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Code Club has been growing in schools thanks to the efforts of Anelisa together with WCED and SADTU and we now (May 2024) 
have 90+ school clubs and 4 community Coderdojos in the Western Cape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re curious to see if there is already a club near you, you can check out:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;code club: &lt;a href=&quot;https://codeclub.org/en/clubs?clubs_search%5Bcountry%5D=ZA&amp;amp;clubs_search%5Bq%5D=cape+town&amp;amp;commit=Find+a+Code+Club&quot;&gt;find a Code Club&lt;/a&gt; (change the location and range to find more clubs)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CoderDojo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://coderdojo.com/en/find?search=cape+town&amp;amp;distance=50&amp;amp;unit=miles&amp;amp;lat=&amp;amp;lng=&quot;&gt;find a Dojo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even more venues coming soon:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Schools: Our Region has has 1500 schools, 97% with computer rooms with internet, and we’ve partnering with WCED to train teachers to start clubs, so more schools coming soon.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Libraries: we’re piloting &lt;a href=&quot;https://help.coderdojo.com/cdkb/s/article/CoderDojo-in-the-library&quot;&gt;CoderDojo in the Library&lt;/a&gt; with Cape Town City Libraries identifying an initial 5-10 libraries, which means any of the 104 (yep!) libraries in the city will be potential pilots, and ultimately we’d like to see them all running.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;volunteering&quot;&gt;Volunteering&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we’re growing, and venues are opening up to be willing to host or starting clubs more volunteers are needed. More volunteers at clubs help get a better outcome for young people across the network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re here to help you be a great volunteer, whether you’re a coder, an educator, a parent or anything in-between.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More info on volunteering:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://codeclub.org/en/volunteer&quot;&gt;https://codeclub.org/en/volunteer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://coderdojo.com/en/volunteer&quot;&gt;https://coderdojo.com/en/volunteer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Training for 1st time volunteers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ideally please do this 30 min safeguarding e-learning module. &lt;a href=&quot;https://projects.raspberrypi.org/en/projects/safeguarding-module/&quot;&gt;https://projects.raspberrypi.org/en/projects/safeguarding-module/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Training for mentoring (helping young people with code):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a good one to review on how / where you’ll be helping. &lt;a href=&quot;https://projects.raspberrypi.org/en/projects/dojo-mentoring/&quot;&gt;https://projects.raspberrypi.org/en/projects/dojo-mentoring/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Specifically, we’ll start most newcomers on “space talk”, the first step in the scratch pathway, that you can play through here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://projects.raspberrypi.org/en/projects/space-talk&quot;&gt;https://projects.raspberrypi.org/en/projects/space-talk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plus there’ll be lots of friendly fellow mentors and teachers along on the journey.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Tue, 09 May 2023 00:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /volunteers-needed</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/volunteers-needed</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>About Code Club</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;Code clubs are school-based extra-mural clubs for young people, practicing coding from first steps through projects in the project pathway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Code Club provides the resources and support to help teachers start successful coding clubs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coder:LevelUp is the Western Cape regional growth partner for the Code Club (and CoderDojo) in a programme sponsored by the Raspberry Pi Foundation. We are helping to train teachers, find volunteers and provide hardware for electronics projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our 2023/2024 goal is 150 new coding clubs across the 1700+ Western Cape schools, with at least 60% from quintile 1-3 schools.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jan 2023 10:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /codeclub</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/codeclub</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Coolest Projects South Africa 2022</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;Coolest Projects is the world’s leading technology fair for young people. This year for the third time in Africa!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Join us for an in-person event in Cape Town on the morning of Saturday 10 December 2022, at Innovation City.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;9:00 Project exhibitors arrive and set up at their desks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;10:00 Open to public / friends / judging starts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;12:00 Ceremony, judges awards&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The event is open to the public to come and see the coolest projects!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to share your project, please read on for details…&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2022 02:02:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /coolestprojects2022</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/coolestprojects2022</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>48 Hour Truly Global Day of CodeRetreat 2022</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;Developers from around the world gathered online for the 48 hours of the “day” of CodeRetreat in our virtual space-station.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Mon, 07 Nov 2022 09:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /globaldayofcoderetreat2022-48hr</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/globaldayofcoderetreat2022-48hr</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Global Day of CodeRetreat 2021</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;Thousands of developers participated on Nov 12-Nov 13, 2021 in the largest free community workshop worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Sun, 07 Nov 2021 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /globaldayofcoderetreat2021</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/globaldayofcoderetreat2021</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>About devdev</title>
        
          <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;devdev&quot;&gt;devdev&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is &lt;strong&gt;dev&lt;/strong&gt;eloping professional &lt;strong&gt;dev&lt;/strong&gt;elopers. A working group with IITPSA (SA professional body for IT professionals).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;devdev’s primary goal is making it &lt;strong&gt;easier to employ and be employed&lt;/strong&gt; in this profession.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Tue, 20 Apr 2021 10:10:10 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /devdev</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/devdev</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Coolest Projects South Africa 2020</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;Coolest Projects is the world’s leading technology fair for young people. This year for the first time in Africa!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to the remote world this year, we’re running Coolest Projects South Africa 100% online, so you can submit from anywhere.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2020 02:02:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /coolestprojects2020</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/coolestprojects2020</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>A coder's journey</title>
        
          <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;a-coders-journey&quot;&gt;A coder’s journey&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kylie is 6, missing 2 front teeth, and is loving code club. Her current focus is Sploder; an arcade game that gives agency to the child by allowing the player to choose whatever monsters or challenges they want their character to face. The player builds the shape of the landscape, the “energy” rewards, the challenges to overcome and then plays their game. We have evolved a lot since the 80s arcade!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sploder was not Kylie’s entry point for learning to code. There are some amazing games and apps out there, and her first toe-dip was an incredible game called Sprite Box. We live in a world of abstractions, you want to travel from A to B, and there is a bus company, train service, taxi, or car manufacturer who is handing out the solution to get you there. You, quite literally, do not have to worry about the mechanics of how to travel. Learning to code has undergone a similar revolution in abstraction. Kids do not need to write to learn to create algorithms or loops. With Sprite Box, kids do not even have to be able to read to grasp coding concepts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sprite box challenges the young coder to create solutions using pre-set methods while forcing them to practice DRY (do not repeat yourself) techniques by limiting the number of actions that they may apply. From the start, Kylie was forced to consider what behaviours her little robot, responsible for assisting her (male or female) character to complete her mission of repairing her space ship, was going to do. The concept of enforcing efficiency in code by building functions to call was implicit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kylie joined in on this adventure at Coder Dojo, a weekly club held at the Cape Town Science Centre for kids interested in coding. As an ex-high school teacher, I find Coder Dojo a relaxing place to hang out because it fits all of my educational desires for any child. This is a pull education, not a push education. There is no curriculum, and the children simply follow their interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are kids immersed in Minecraft, Raspberry pie builds, or apps such as Scratch, Algorithm City, Sploder, and Ozaria. They may be found designing their own website or troubleshooting their python code. What they are involved in depends entirely on what their interests are. They work in groups, and they work alone. What is clearly apparent to an ex-mainstream teacher, is that they are all avidly involved in their work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is your child interested in coding? Do you perhaps have no idea whether your child is interested in coding? Either way, feel welcome and come and join in.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Sun, 15 Mar 2020 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /coderjourney</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/coderjourney</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>About CoderDojo</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;Free coding clubs for young people, practicing coding from first steps through projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coder:LevelUp is the regional growth partner for the CoderDojo Foundation.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2019 10:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /coderdojo</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/coderdojo</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Welcome to CoderLevelUp</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;Hey! Welcome to CoderLevelUp, it’s great to have you :)qw&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jan 2019 22:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /welcome</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/welcome</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>About CodeRetreat</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;Day-long event pair programming with new people sharing practices and perfect practice.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jan 2019 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /coderetreat</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/coderetreat</guid>
      </item>
      
    
  </channel>
</rss>
